<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><w:document xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main" xmlns:m="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/math" xmlns:r="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/relationships" xmlns:o="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:office" xmlns:v="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:vml" xmlns:w10="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:word" xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main" xmlns:pic="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/picture" xmlns:wp="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/wordprocessingDrawing"><w:body><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Title" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Bridging the Gap: Trust, Competence, and Concern in the Integration of AI among Teachers and Students</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Author" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Daniele Dragoni, Rino Falcone, Elisa Colì, Isabella Poggi, Daniele Caligiore</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:sdt><w:sdtPr><w:docPartObj><w:docPartGallery w:val="Table of Contents" /><w:docPartUnique /></w:docPartObj></w:sdtPr><w:sdtContent><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="TOCHeading" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Table of Contents</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:r><w:fldChar w:fldCharType="begin" w:dirty="true" /><w:instrText xml:space="preserve">TOC \o &quot;1-3&quot; \h \z \u</w:instrText><w:fldChar w:fldCharType="separate" /><w:fldChar w:fldCharType="end" /></w:r></w:p></w:sdtContent></w:sdt><w:bookmarkStart w:id="20" w:name="introduction" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Introduction</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Educational institutions worldwide face an unprecedented challenge: Generative Artificial Intelligence (GenAI) has already been massively adopted by students, yet this integration is occurring without adequate guidance, critical frameworks, or pedagogical support. Our research documents a critical paradox at the heart of contemporary education. Eighty percent of students use Artificial Intelligence (AI) daily, compared to significantly lower adoption rates among teachers. This substantial usage gap reveals a fundamental misalignment between the intensity of AI use and the preparedness of institutional actors. Moreover, both groups report that the formal training they have received is grossly inadequate. Beyond this, teachers express profound concerns about students’ capacity for responsible AI use—a concern that becomes particularly acute given the inadequacy of formal guidance available to both educators and learners.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This study investigates the current state of AI adoption in Italian educational contexts, revealing a troubling gap between intensive usage and critical competence. We examine how students and teachers perceive their AI skills, what tools they employ, how much trust exists in AI integration, and what concerns emerge about responsible use. Our findings suggest an urgent educational challenge: while students are developing AI competencies through valuable informal learning channels—peer-to-peer knowledge sharing and experiential exploration—educational institutions have lagged behind in providing the complementary formal frameworks, critical scaffolding, and pedagogical guidance necessary to deepen this learning into genuine critical</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="20" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="21" w:name="X0da053f2f11cd4bda077d816e9905a6567c2e1e" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">GenAI as Cultural Mediator: Transformative Potential and Critical Limitations</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">GenAI functions as a bridge between human and machine language, operating as an interface uniquely capable of translating between natural human communication and computational logic. This linguistic capability means that users can now express complex intentions in natural language, and GenAI converts these into actionable digital outputs. However, this technical bridge conceals a deeper cultural transformation. GenAI represents a new form of mediation between users and knowledge itself—creating an additional layer of distance and interpretation in how we access, create, and understand information.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This mediation function is fundamentally new. Unlike previous educational technologies that retrieve or display existing information, GenAI synthesizes and recombines knowledge in novel configurations. Bruno Munari, in his work</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Fantasia</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Munari, 1977)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, suggests that creativity involves recombining existing elements to generate new configurations. GenAI operates precisely through such recombinatory processes, presenting its outputs as natural and intuitive. Yet this apparent simplicity masks complex underlying processes and introduces critical questions of authenticity, reliability, and epistemic authority. As a cultural mediator, GenAI mediates not only access to information but also shapes how we construct meaning, solve problems, and imagine possibilities.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The practical implications of this mediating function are substantial. Students and educators can now create interactive digital materials previously requiring specialized technical expertise: dynamic websites, interactive dashboards, assessment simulations, and personalized learning experiences such as avatar-based interactions with historical or literary figures. This democratization of digital creation is transformative.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">However, this new mediation introduces significant risks that demand critical institutional attention. GenAI systems are inherently imprecise and prone to reproducing the biases embedded in their training data. These systems do not generate neutral outputs; they perpetuate and amplify the discriminatory patterns present in the data they were trained on. Consequently, their use in educational contexts—particularly in assessment and evaluation—poses substantial ethical and pedagogical risks. The European Union, through the AI Act</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">EU AI Act (Regulation (EU) 2024/1689)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, 2024)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, has designated education as a high-risk domain, precisely because of these concerns. The AI Act restricts the use of AI systems in education, particularly prohibiting their deployment for evaluative purposes without human supervision. Any application of GenAI in educational settings must therefore be subject to rigorous oversight, with qualified educators maintaining full authority over consequential decisions affecting students. The apparent capability and efficiency of these systems cannot override the fundamental requirement for human judgment and accountability in educational contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="21" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="22" w:name="research-objectives" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Research objectives</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This article reports findings from a quantitative survey examining whether schools, universities, students, and teachers are ready to face the AI transformation and how they are experiencing it.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The urgency of this investigation stems from rapid changes in educational technology landscapes: Generative AI tools have become widely available to students and teachers, yet questions remain about how these technologies are being integrated, what competencies are being developed, and what challenges educational institutions face in supporting effective adoption. This study systematically examines key dimensions of AI integration in Italian educational contexts to understand the current state of readiness and identify areas requiring attention.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">We translated the overarching research question—</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Are educational stakeholders ready for AI transformation?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">—into six specific, measurable dimensions that capture both behavioral patterns and psychological factors of AI adoption. These dimensions form an interconnected framework for understanding readiness: actual practices, self-perceived capabilities, institutional support, psychological predispositions, barriers to adoption, and expectations for change.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Establishing</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">usage patterns</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">provides the empirical foundation for the entire investigation. Without grounding the study in behavioral reality—understanding how frequently, intensively, and diversely AI tools are actually being employed—assessments of competence, trust, or concerns risk floating in abstraction. This dimension reveals the extent of AI diffusion in educational practice, creating the baseline against which to evaluate whether stakeholders’ psychological readiness aligns with their actual engagement. Measuring usage also allows us to identify disparities between different groups, which is essential for understanding whether AI integration is proceeding uniformly or creating new divides.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">However, usage alone cannot reveal whether engagement is superficial or informed.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived competence</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">addresses this gap by distinguishing between practical ability (operational use of tools) and theoretical understanding (comprehension of mechanisms, capabilities, and limitations). This distinction is critical: high usage coupled with low theoretical competence suggests potentially uncritical adoption, while high theoretical knowledge with low practical skills indicates unrealized potential. By measuring both dimensions across students and teachers, we can identify whether stakeholders possess the depth of understanding necessary for critical, responsible use rather than merely instrumental familiarity. Competence perceptions also function as indicators of self-efficacy, which research consistently shows influences technology adoption and sustained engagement.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The gap between current competence and needed competence points directly to institutional responsibility, making</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">training adequacy</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">a crucial dimension. Evaluating whether formal preparation efforts meet stakeholders’ needs reveals the effectiveness of educational systems’ responses to AI transformation. Are institutions proactively equipping their communities, or are users navigating this landscape without adequate support? This dimension identifies where policy interventions and resource allocation are most urgently needed, distinguishing between contexts where infrastructure exists but is insufficient versus contexts where institutional support is largely absent.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Yet even adequate training cannot guarantee effective integration if psychological barriers persist.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust and confidence</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">operate as gatekeepers to adoption: stakeholders who lack confidence in AI’s reliability or appropriateness in educational contexts—or, for teachers, who distrust students’ capacity for responsible use—will resist integration regardless of competence or training. We measure trust as both a facilitator and obstacle, recognizing that rational adoption depends not only on capability but on belief in the technology’s value and in human actors’ ability to use it appropriately. This dimension reveals whether resistance stems from knowledge gaps (addressable through training) or fundamental skepticism about AI’s role in education (requiring deeper pedagogical dialogue).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust’s counterpart is</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">concern</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: while trust measures confidence in positive outcomes, concerns capture anxieties about risks. Understanding the nature and intensity of these worries—whether focused on academic integrity, skill atrophy, bias, privacy, or pedagogical disruption—helps identify the psychological barriers that inhibit adoption. Concerns also indicate perceived urgency: high levels of worry signal that stakeholders recognize AI integration as a pressing issue requiring immediate attention, while low concern might suggest either complacency or lack of awareness. By mapping the landscape of anxieties, we can address specific fears through targeted interventions rather than generic reassurances.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Finally,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">perceived change</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">captures whether stakeholders anticipate transformation and how they conceptualize it. Expectations about AI’s impact on teaching practices and learning methods reveal readiness for adaptation: realistic anticipation of change suggests psychological preparation, while denial of impact or unrealistic expectations (whether utopian or dystopian) indicate potential resistance or disappointment. For teachers, we measure both self-directed expectations (impact on my own teaching) and other-directed perceptions (impact on teaching generally), as discrepancies between these perspectives can signal defensive attitudes toward change. Understanding these expectations helps institutions manage the transformation process, aligning stakeholder anticipations with realistic trajectories.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Together, these six dimensions create a comprehensive diagnostic framework. Usage patterns establish what is happening; perceived competence reveals whether users understand what they are doing; training adequacy indicates whether institutions are supporting the transition; trust and confidence measure psychological readiness to embrace AI; concerns identify barriers and perceived urgency; and perceived change captures expectations for transformation. By examining these dimensions in tandem across students and teachers in Italian educational contexts, we can construct a nuanced portrait of readiness that moves beyond simplistic adoption metrics to reveal the complex interplay of behavior, knowledge, institutional support, and psychological factors shaping AI integration in education.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="22" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="27" w:name="theoretical-framework" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Theoretical Framework</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Understanding AI integration in education requires theoretical lenses that capture both individual psychological processes and socio-cognitive dynamics. This study draws upon complementary frameworks from cognitive psychology, technology adoption research, and innovation diffusion theory to interpret the six dimensions examined: usage patterns, perceived competence, training adequacy, trust, concerns, and perceived change. These frameworks provide theoretical grounding for understanding how educators and students navigate AI adoption—cognitively, emotionally, and behaviorally.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="23" w:name="X34aacd8b18f824f678cd9fc73477c124b5dabe1" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">4.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Socio-Cognitive Foundations: Mind, Behavior, and Trust</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The theoretical framework draws upon the cognitive and social model developed by Castelfranchi and colleagues</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Castelfranchi et al., 2002; Castelfranchi &amp; Parisi, 1980; Castelfranchi &amp; Poggi, 1998; Conte &amp; Castelfranchi, 1995; Miceli &amp; Castelfranchi, 1989, 1995, 2002; Poggi, 2006, 2022; Poggi, 2008)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, which provides a comprehensive understanding of mental attitudes, social cognition, and behavioral dynamics in complex social contexts. This model offers analytical tools for interpreting the cognitive and emotional dimensions underlying participants’ responses about AI adoption, competence perceptions, and attitudes toward technology integration in education.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A central component of this theoretical foundation is the construct of interpersonal trust elaborated by Castelfranchi and Falcone</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Castelfranchi &amp; Falcone, 2017; Falcone &amp; Castelfranchi, 2008)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. According to their socio-cognitive model, trust is viewed as a complex mental attitude based on the beliefs and goals of the trusting subject. Trust is placed in another when one believes that the other has both the capacity and the willingness to perform a certain task in a way that satisfies one’s own purpose. Translating this perspective to the educational context, trust toward AI can be understood as the belief that AI is capable of effectively supporting the achievement of educational objectives. The literature demonstrates how trust influences the acceptance of AI technologies: only when perceived as reliable and aligned with their educational goals will teachers and students be inclined to integrate them into daily practices</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Allison &amp; Blair, 2025)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. This dimension proves crucial given the heterogeneous attitudes toward AI in educational contexts, ranging from enthusiasm to skepticism.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Complementing the trust framework is Bandura’s self-efficacy theory</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Bandura, 1977, 1986)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, which posits that individuals’ beliefs about their capabilities to perform specific tasks fundamentally shape their motivation, behavior, and resilience when facing challenges. Self-efficacy derives from four primary sources: mastery experiences (successful task completion), vicarious experiences (observing others), social persuasion (encouragement from others), and physiological states (stress or confidence). In technology contexts, technology self-efficacy—the belief in one’s ability to successfully use technological tools—has been consistently shown to predict adoption, sustained engagement, and willingness to explore advanced features</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Compeau &amp; Higgins, 1995)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. In our framework, self-efficacy helps explain the distinction between practical competence (operational ability) and theoretical competence (conceptual understanding): individuals with high self-efficacy are more likely to move beyond surface-level use toward deeper, critical engagement with AI tools. Moreover, self-efficacy interacts with trust: while trust addresses what the technology can do reliably, self-efficacy addresses what I can do with the technology competently.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="23" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="24" w:name="Xe66571d4f226ff815119b950e384a55eb9041c1" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">4.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Technology Adoption: The Role of Perceived Usefulness and Ease of Use</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">To understand the transition from awareness to actual use, we draw on the Technology Acceptance Model (TAM)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Davis, 1989)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, one of the most empirically validated frameworks for predicting technology adoption. TAM proposes that two key beliefs drive behavioral intention to use technology: perceived usefulness (PU)—the degree to which using a system enhances performance—and perceived ease of use (PEOU)—the degree to which using a system is free from effort. Meta-analytic research on teachers’ technology adoption demonstrates that both constructs significantly predict integration behavior, with PU often mediated by PEOU</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Scherer et al., 2019)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. TAM connects directly to our study’s competence dimension: perceived competence influences PEOU (those who feel competent perceive tools as easier to use), while perceived usefulness aligns with our trust measure (belief that AI can reliably support educational goals). External variables such as training adequacy and institutional support function as antecedents to both PU and PEOU, creating pathways through which institutional interventions can facilitate adoption. By measuring both perceived competence and usage patterns, we can assess whether the TAM pathway—from competence beliefs through ease-of-use perceptions to actual adoption—holds in AI educational contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="24" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="25" w:name="Xb8173aa3bc1b2fa2285a9a079cf7c14e63bfd90" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">4.3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Psychological Barriers: Anxiety and Concerns in Innovation Adoption</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">While trust and competence facilitate adoption, psychological barriers can inhibit it. Recent research on AI anxiety reveals a nuanced relationship between use and apprehension: a U-shaped pattern emerges where minimal AI use triggers anticipatory anxiety (fear of unknown consequences), moderate use reduces anxiety by building familiarity and control, but excessive use can generate dependency anxiety (fear of over-reliance and loss of autonomy)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Frenkenberg &amp; Hochman, 2025)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. This framework helps interpret the nature and intensity of concerns we measure: are worries driven by unfamiliarity (addressable through exposure) or by deeper ethical and existential fears (requiring substantive dialogue)?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Complementing anxiety research is the Concerns-Based Adoption Model (CBAM)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Hall &amp; Hord, 1987)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, developed specifically for educational innovations. CBAM identifies a developmental progression through stages of concern: initially, individuals exhibit self-focused concerns (Will I be able to learn this? How will it affect my workload?), which gradually shift to task-focused concerns (How do I manage implementation effectively?) and ultimately to impact-focused concerns (How does this benefit students? How can I refine my practice?). This progression model suggests that concerns are not static obstacles but evolving psychological states that change with experience and support. By measuring concerns across teachers and students at different adoption stages, we can diagnose where stakeholders are positioned along this developmental trajectory and what interventions might facilitate progression toward impact-focused engagement rather than remaining stalled in self-focused apprehension.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="25" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="26" w:name="Xc2fe9b36ca8d21a644cdbdcc0ac6f29efe9e425" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">4.4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Integrating Frameworks: A Comprehensive Model of AI Readiness</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">These theoretical frameworks converge to create a multi-dimensional model of AI readiness in education. Usage patterns provide the behavioral foundation, revealing the extent of diffusion. Self-efficacy and TAM’s perceived competence constructs explain why some individuals engage confidently while others hesitate. Trust (Castelfranchi-Falcone) captures the relational and cognitive belief that AI can reliably support educational goals, while AI anxiety and CBAM’s stages of concern illuminate the psychological barriers that impede adoption even when competence and trust exist. Training adequacy functions as an institutional moderator, potentially strengthening self-efficacy, reducing anxiety, and building trust. Finally, perceived change reflects meta-cognitive awareness of transformation, signaling psychological preparedness (or resistance) to adaptation. Together, these frameworks enable us to move beyond simplistic binary classifications (adopters vs. non-adopters) toward a nuanced understanding of AI integration as a complex interplay of cognitive beliefs, emotional states, social trust, institutional support, and developmental progression. The empirical findings that follow are interpreted through these theoretical lenses, revealing not merely what is happening, but why—and what interventions might effectively support readiness across diverse educational contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="26" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="27" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="34" w:name="materials-and-methods" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Materials and Methods</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A quantitative survey design with action-research components was implemented to capture numerical trends and measurable patterns in AI adoption in education. The study employed traditional survey techniques enhanced by an experimental</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">vibe-research</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">approach, whereby an interactive dashboard facilitated a dynamic interplay between GenAI and researcher decisions, allowing real-time adjustments to question presentation and analytic focus.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="28" w:name="questionnaire-design" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Questionnaire Design</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The primary data collection instrument was an online questionnaire structured around four domains:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The questionnaire was structured around three main categories of items:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1001" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Usage patterns</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Binary (yes/no) questions and numeric items captured actual AI adoption behaviors:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Daily AI use in everyday life (yes/no)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">AI use specifically for educational purposes—teaching for instructors, studying for students (yes/no)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Weekly hours dedicated to AI-supported activities (numeric)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Weekly hours dedicated to learning about new AI tools (numeric)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Weekly time saved through AI use (numeric, students only)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Weekly hours integrating AI into lesson planning (numeric, teachers only)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Specific AI tools employed (multiple choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Purposes for which AI is used (multiple choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Activities for which AI should</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">not</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">be used (multiple choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Difficulties encountered in AI implementation (multiple choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1002" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived advantages and disadvantages of AI use (multiple choice, students only)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1001" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Competence and training</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Seven-point Likert scales (1 = not at all, 7 = extremely) measured:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1003" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived practical competence in using AI tools (Students #8, Teachers #10)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1003" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived theoretical understanding of AI principles and mechanisms (Students #9, Teachers #11)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1003" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Adequacy of formal training received on AI (Students #11, Teachers #14)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1003" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived competence of teachers in teaching AI use (Students #13, teachers’ perspective)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1001" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust, confidence, and concerns</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Seven-point Likert scales assessed psychological dimensions:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1004" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Confidence in AI integration in education (Students #12, Teachers #15)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1004" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust in students’ responsible use of AI (Teachers #16, students’ self-assessment via #15)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1004" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Level of concern about AI integration in education (Students #14, Teachers #17)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1004" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Level of concern about students’ AI use (Students #15, Teachers #18)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="1" /><w:numId w:val="1004" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Expected impact of AI on study methods (Students #10) or on teaching practices generally (Teachers #12) and personally (Teachers #13)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Mirror-formulated items across student and teacher questionnaires ensured direct comparability, enabling systematic analysis of perspective alignment or divergence between these groups. Question numbering varied between cohorts but content remained parallel where applicable (see Appendix for complete question listing). Prior to deployment, the questionnaire underwent pilot testing with a small convenience sample to refine wording, verify response consistency, and estimate completion time.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="28" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="29" w:name="participants" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Participants</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The study involved three primary participant groups, with teacher participants constituting the majority of the sample. Most teachers were actively engaged in professional development programs at the time of data collection. These included educators enrolled in mandatory qualification pathways required under recent Italian educational reforms—specifically PEF30, PEF60, and TFA (Tirocinio Formativo Attivo) programs for teaching licensure, as well as specialized support teacher training courses (corsi per il sostegno). Additionally, a substantial portion of teacher participants were attending professional updating courses specifically focused on AI integration and digital competencies in education. This population represents a strategically significant cohort for understanding faculty development needs, as these educators are actively engaged in updating their professional knowledge and pedagogical approaches to incorporate emerging technologies.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The second teacher subgroup consisted of pre-service teachers: university students enrolled in teacher education programs preparing for future teaching careers. This group complements the in-service professional development participants by representing another dimension of teacher formation—initial preparation rather than ongoing professional updating.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Student participants were drawn from two educational contexts. Secondary school students were recruited through the in-service teachers who participated in the study, creating a direct connection between educator professional development contexts and student learning environments. University students, primarily enrolled in psychology programs, served as a counterpart to the teacher training populations (PEF and TFA participants), representing another domain of higher education formation. Together, these student groups enabled examination of AI adoption patterns across different educational levels and institutional contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Recruitment occurred primarily through faculty development courses, teacher training programs, educational networks, and university courses, with additional online invitations extending participation opportunities. The sampling strategy deliberately prioritized educators engaged in professional learning contexts, as this population is strategically positioned at the intersection of current practice and institutional transformation efforts—actively navigating the challenges of integrating AI into their teaching while simultaneously developing the competencies necessary to do so effectively. This focus aligns directly with the study’s emphasis on understanding readiness, competence gaps, and capacity-building needs during AI integration in education.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="29" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="30" w:name="data-collection-procedures" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5.3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Data Collection Procedures</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Data collection extended over several weeks during the academic term, employing a dual-modality approach designed to balance accessibility with pedagogical value. While a portion of participants completed the questionnaire independently through a web-based platform, the majority engaged with the survey during university lectures and professional development courses. This in-class administration proved particularly valuable: after completing the questionnaire, participants engaged in facilitated group reflections on AI use in educational contexts. These discussions transformed data collection from a purely extractive research activity into a generative pedagogical opportunity, enabling participants to critically examine their own practices and assumptions about AI integration while simultaneously contributing to the research. This approach not only ensured substantially higher response rates but also created immediate value for participants, who reported that the reflection process itself heightened their awareness of AI-related challenges and opportunities.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">All responses were gathered under strict adherence to GDPR regulations, with complete anonymization protocols ensuring that no individual participant could be identified from the data. Participation was entirely voluntary, with no financial incentives or course credit offered, thereby mitigating potential response biases related to coercion or external reward. Participants were free to skip any questions they preferred not to answer and could withdraw from the study at any point without consequence.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="30" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="31" w:name="ethical-considerations" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5.4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Ethical Considerations</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The study design incorporated comprehensive ethical safeguards throughout all phases of the research. Before beginning the questionnaire, all participants received detailed information about the study’s purposes, the nature of questions they would encounter, how their data would be used, and the protections in place to ensure confidentiality. This informed consent process emphasized that participation was voluntary and that they could withdraw at any time without providing justification.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Data protection measures extended beyond basic anonymization. All collected data were stored on secure servers with access restricted to the research team, and storage protocols complied fully with European data protection regulations. No personally identifying information was collected as part of the questionnaire responses, and demographic data (age, gender, educational role) were gathered only in aggregate form sufficient for analytical purposes but insufficient for individual identification. These ethical protections were particularly important given that some questions addressed potentially sensitive topics, such as self-assessed competence levels and concerns about professional adequacy, where participants needed assurance that their candid responses would not expose them to professional or academic consequences.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="31" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="32" w:name="statistical-analysis" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5.5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Statistical Analysis</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The quantitative analysis employed standard statistical procedures to identify patterns and test hypotheses across participant groups. Descriptive statistics (means, medians, standard deviations, and frequency distributions) provided the foundational characterization of response patterns, revealing central tendencies and variability within each measured dimension. To detect statistically significant differences between students and teachers, we conducted independent-samples t-tests on key variables including perceived competence, trust levels, and training adequacy ratings. For comparisons involving three groups (current teachers, future teachers, and students), one-way ANOVAs enabled simultaneous examination of between-group variations. Finally, correlation matrices illuminated the relationships among variables, revealing whether perceived competence, concerns, trust, and actual usage patterns showed meaningful associations that might suggest causal or predictive relationships warranting further investigation.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="32" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="33" w:name="ai-assisted-research-methodology" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5.6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">AI-Assisted Research Methodology</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This study adopted an innovative methodological approach that aligned research practice with research subject matter: investigating AI integration in education while simultaneously employing AI tools throughout the research process itself. This reflexive methodology transformed the research team into participant-observers, experiencing firsthand the affordances and challenges that survey respondents reported.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The research workflow integrated human intellectual work with AI assistance at multiple stages, following a consistent pattern: independent human-generated initial work, followed by AI-assisted refinement and verification. Writing proceeded iteratively, with researchers drafting content autonomously and then employing advanced AI coding assistants—specifically Anthropic’s Claude Code, OpenAI’s Codex, GitHub Copilot, and integrated AI capabilities within Visual Studio Code—to refine argumentation, enhance clarity, identify conceptual gaps, and suggest relevant literature. Importantly, these tools represent sophisticated programming environments that extend far beyond simple conversational AI interfaces, providing context-aware code generation, automated script creation, and intelligent debugging capabilities. Critically, every AI-generated suggestion—whether textual, analytical, or bibliographic—underwent rigorous human verification to ensure accuracy, appropriateness, and scholarly integrity. No AI output entered the final manuscript without critical evaluation and confirmation of its validity.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">For data analysis and visualization, the research employed a custom interactive dashboard developed using a modern web technology stack: Vite for the frontend framework, Python for backend data processing, and PostgreSQL for data storage. The development process exemplified AI-human collaboration: researchers articulated analytical goals and visualization requirements in natural language, AI coding assistants generated implementation code, and researchers reviewed, debugged, and refined the outputs to ensure statistical validity and interpretive accuracy. This</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">vibecoding</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">approach—where high-level intentions are translated into functional code through AI mediation—dramatically accelerated development while maintaining analytical rigor through human oversight. Scripts for automated data processing, statistical analysis, and visualization generation were developed collaboratively between human researchers and AI assistants, with version control tracking the iterative refinement process.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The project embraces full methodological transparency through open-source practices. Both the data analysis platform and this manuscript are maintained in public GitHub repositories, enabling full reproducibility and scholarly scrutiny of research methods, code implementations, and analytical decisions. This transparency reflects our commitment to accountable AI-assisted research: all workflows, prompts, AI-generated code, and human modifications are documented and accessible, allowing the scholarly community to examine exactly how AI tools contributed to the research process and how human oversight ensured validity.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The project repository structure itself reflects this hybrid methodology, organized to support both human comprehension and AI-assisted workflows. Documentation files explain research objectives and methodological decisions; data processing scripts contain human-readable comments alongside AI-generated code; and version control practices track the evolution of both human and AI contributions. This transparent workflow enabled the research team to maintain full accountability for all analytical decisions while leveraging AI capabilities for efficiency and exploratory analysis.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This methodological transparency serves dual purposes. First, it models responsible AI integration in research practice, demonstrating how these tools can enhance rather than replace human scholarly judgment. Second, it provides the research team with experiential knowledge of AI adoption challenges—the same uncertainties, learning curves, trust negotiations, and competence development that our participants reported. This first-person engagement with AI tools informed our interpretation of survey findings, grounding theoretical analysis in lived methodological experience.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="33" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="34" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="64" w:name="results" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Results</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The results section presents the main findings of the study, structured around several key thematic areas. It begins with the demographic profile of participants, then moves to an analysis of how artificial intelligence is utilized in teaching and learning environments. Following this, the report explores participants’ perceptions of their own competencies, their levels of trust and concern regarding AI, the time dedicated to AI-related activities, and the specific tools employed.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="35" w:name="principal-findings" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Principal findings</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Our investigation reveals several critical insights:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1005" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A substantial usage gap exists between students (80% daily users) and teachers, reflecting different needs, affordances, and barriers to adoption</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1005" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A significant competence paradox: users demonstrate practical skills in operating AI tools but lack theoretical understanding of underlying mechanisms, limitations, and biases</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1005" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Widespread dissatisfaction with formal AI training among both students and teachers, with over a quarter rating it as completely inadequate</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1005" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A notable trust asymmetry: students express greater confidence in AI integration than teachers, while teachers harbor significant concerns about students’ capacity for critical and responsible use</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1005" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Concentration of usage around a single generalist platform (ChatGPT), with limited awareness of specialized educational tools</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1005" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A psychological</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">third-person bias</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">among teachers, who recognize AI’s transformative potential for education generally but are less certain about its impact on their personal teaching practices</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">These findings illuminate both the urgent need for structured institutional intervention and the complex psychological, pedagogical, and ethical dimensions that must be addressed to ensure responsible and effective AI integration in educational settings.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="35" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="39" w:name="participant-demographics" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Participant Demographics</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The study is based on three participant categories: students (n = 269), teachers currently in service (n = 356), and prospective teachers in training (n = 99). Age differences between these groups are substantial, with a 25-year gap between the student median (22 anni) and the teacher median (46 anni), while future teachers occupy an intermediate position (mediana = 36 anni).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Table 1: Age distribution summary by participant category</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:tbl><w:tblPr><w:tblStyle w:val="Table" /><w:tblW w:type="pct" w:w="5000" /><w:tblLayout w:type="fixed" /><w:tblLook w:firstRow="1" w:lastRow="0" w:firstColumn="0" w:lastColumn="0" w:noHBand="0" w:noVBand="0" w:val="0020" /></w:tblPr><w:tblGrid><w:gridCol w:w="2428" /><w:gridCol w:w="844" /><w:gridCol w:w="633" /><w:gridCol w:w="844" /><w:gridCol w:w="739" /><w:gridCol w:w="739" /><w:gridCol w:w="633" /><w:gridCol w:w="528" /><w:gridCol w:w="528" /></w:tblGrid><w:tr><w:trPr><w:tblHeader w:val="on" /></w:trPr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Group</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Sample</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Mean</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Median</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><m:oMath><m:sSub><m:e><m:r><m:t>Q</m:t></m:r></m:e><m:sub><m:r><m:t>1</m:t></m:r></m:sub></m:sSub></m:oMath></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><m:oMath><m:sSub><m:e><m:r><m:t>Q</m:t></m:r></m:e><m:sub><m:r><m:t>3</m:t></m:r></m:sub></m:sSub></m:oMath></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">IQR</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Min</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Max</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">269</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">21.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">22.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">17.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">23.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">14</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">58</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers (current)</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">356</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">45.6</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">46.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">39.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">53.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">14.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">20</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">72</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers (pre-service)</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">99</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">36.6</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">36.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">29.5</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">43.0</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">13.5</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">22</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="right" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">56</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr></w:tbl><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Note.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Sample = number of participants;</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><m:oMath><m:sSub><m:e><m:r><m:t>Q</m:t></m:r></m:e><m:sub><m:r><m:t>1</m:t></m:r></m:sub></m:sSub></m:oMath><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">and</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><m:oMath><m:sSub><m:e><m:r><m:t>Q</m:t></m:r></m:e><m:sub><m:r><m:t>3</m:t></m:r></m:sub></m:sSub></m:oMath><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">= first and third quartile; IQR = interquartile range; Min/Max = observed minimum and maximum.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="CaptionedFigure" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:drawing><wp:inline><wp:extent cx="3840480" cy="2902673" /><wp:effectExtent b="0" l="0" r="0" t="0" /><wp:docPr descr="Figure 1. Age distribution by participant category (violin plots)." title="" id="37" name="Picture" /><a:graphic><a:graphicData uri="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/picture"><pic:pic><pic:nvPicPr><pic:cNvPr descr="assets/figures/age_violin.png" id="38" name="Picture" /><pic:cNvPicPr><a:picLocks noChangeArrowheads="1" noChangeAspect="1" /></pic:cNvPicPr></pic:nvPicPr><pic:blipFill><a:blip r:embed="rId36" /><a:stretch><a:fillRect /></a:stretch></pic:blipFill><pic:spPr bwMode="auto"><a:xfrm><a:off x="0" y="0" /><a:ext cx="3840480" cy="2902673" /></a:xfrm><a:prstGeom prst="rect"><a:avLst /></a:prstGeom><a:noFill /><a:ln w="9525"><a:noFill /><a:headEnd /><a:tailEnd /></a:ln></pic:spPr></pic:pic></a:graphicData></a:graphic></wp:inline></w:drawing></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="ImageCaption" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Figure 1. Age distribution by participant category (violin plots).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Figure 1 displays the age distribution across the three groups using violin plots, which combine box plot elements with kernel density estimation to reveal both central tendencies and the full shape of each distribution. The figure clearly illustrates the generational separation between students (concentrated in their early twenties) and in-service teachers (predominantly in their forties and fifties), with pre-service teachers forming a bridge population in their thirties.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="39" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="51" w:name="ai-usage-patterns" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">AI Usage Patterns</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="49" w:name="daily-and-educational-use" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.3.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Daily and Educational Use</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A striking finding concerns the substantial gap between AI utilization by students and teachers. Approximately 80% of students report using AI tools daily, compared to significantly lower rates among current and future teachers. This disparity extends to both general daily use and specific educational applications (studying for students, teaching preparation for teachers).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="CaptionedFigure" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:drawing><wp:inline><wp:extent cx="3840480" cy="2754501" /><wp:effectExtent b="0" l="0" r="0" t="0" /><wp:docPr descr="Figure 2. Weekly hours of AI use by participant category." title="" id="41" name="Picture" /><a:graphic><a:graphicData uri="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/picture"><pic:pic><pic:nvPicPr><pic:cNvPr descr="assets/figures/weekly_ai_hours.png" id="42" name="Picture" /><pic:cNvPicPr><a:picLocks noChangeArrowheads="1" noChangeAspect="1" /></pic:cNvPicPr></pic:nvPicPr><pic:blipFill><a:blip r:embed="rId40" /><a:stretch><a:fillRect /></a:stretch></pic:blipFill><pic:spPr bwMode="auto"><a:xfrm><a:off x="0" y="0" /><a:ext cx="3840480" cy="2754501" /></a:xfrm><a:prstGeom prst="rect"><a:avLst /></a:prstGeom><a:noFill /><a:ln w="9525"><a:noFill /><a:headEnd /><a:tailEnd /></a:ln></pic:spPr></pic:pic></a:graphicData></a:graphic></wp:inline></w:drawing></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="ImageCaption" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Figure 2. Weekly hours of AI use by participant category.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Figure 2 makes this polarization explicit. To preserve readability, the boxplots display the central distribution up to 11 hours per week; the extreme cases are listed separately in Table 2. Students invest a median of 2 hours per week (Q1–Q3 = 1–5 h) and still show a long right tail culminating in 56 hours. In-service teachers display a tighter band (Q1–Q3 = 1–3 h) but include individuals reporting up to 50 hours, whereas pre-service teachers cluster between 2 and 4 hours with a smaller number of intensive users.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Table 2: Extreme weekly AI use cases (hours per week)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:tbl><w:tblPr><w:tblStyle w:val="Table" /><w:tblW w:type="pct" w:w="5000" /><w:tblLayout w:type="fixed" /><w:tblLook w:firstRow="1" w:lastRow="0" w:firstColumn="0" w:lastColumn="0" w:noHBand="0" w:noVBand="0" w:val="0020" /></w:tblPr><w:tblGrid><w:gridCol w:w="2538" /><w:gridCol w:w="5381" /></w:tblGrid><w:tr><w:trPr><w:tblHeader w:val="on" /></w:trPr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Category</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Outlier hours (h/week)</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">56, 50, 49, 49, 40, 30, 28, 26, 24, 22, 20, 18, 16, 14, 13, 12</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">In-service Teachers</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">50, 30, 20, 15, 15, 12, 12, 11, 10, 10, 9, 8.5, 8.5, 8, 7.5, 7</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Pre-service Teachers</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">10, 10, 8</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr></w:tbl><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="CaptionedFigure" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:drawing><wp:inline><wp:extent cx="3840480" cy="2754501" /><wp:effectExtent b="0" l="0" r="0" t="0" /><wp:docPr descr="Figure 2. Weekly hours dedicated to AI training and tool learning." title="" id="44" name="Picture" /><a:graphic><a:graphicData uri="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/picture"><pic:pic><pic:nvPicPr><pic:cNvPr descr="assets/figures/weekly_ai_training.png" id="45" name="Picture" /><pic:cNvPicPr><a:picLocks noChangeArrowheads="1" noChangeAspect="1" /></pic:cNvPicPr></pic:nvPicPr><pic:blipFill><a:blip r:embed="rId43" /><a:stretch><a:fillRect /></a:stretch></pic:blipFill><pic:spPr bwMode="auto"><a:xfrm><a:off x="0" y="0" /><a:ext cx="3840480" cy="2754501" /></a:xfrm><a:prstGeom prst="rect"><a:avLst /></a:prstGeom><a:noFill /><a:ln w="9525"><a:noFill /><a:headEnd /><a:tailEnd /></a:ln></pic:spPr></pic:pic></a:graphicData></a:graphic></wp:inline></w:drawing></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="ImageCaption" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Figure 2. Weekly hours dedicated to AI training and tool learning.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Self-directed training diverges even more sharply (Figure 2). The central distribution remains close to zero for students (median = 0 h, Q1–Q3 = 0–1 h), while rare intensive efforts reach 40 hours and beyond (see Table 3). In-service teachers record the widest spread (median = 1 h, Q1–Q3 = 0–2 h) with a minority investing dozens—and in one case hundreds—of hours in autonomous upskilling. Pre-service teachers stay intermediate (median = 0 h, Q1–Q3 = 0–1.8 h).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Table 3: Extreme weekly AI training cases (hours per week)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:tbl><w:tblPr><w:tblStyle w:val="Table" /><w:tblW w:type="pct" w:w="5000" /><w:tblLayout w:type="fixed" /><w:tblLook w:firstRow="1" w:lastRow="0" w:firstColumn="0" w:lastColumn="0" w:noHBand="0" w:noVBand="0" w:val="0020" /></w:tblPr><w:tblGrid><w:gridCol w:w="2444" /><w:gridCol w:w="5475" /></w:tblGrid><w:tr><w:trPr><w:tblHeader w:val="on" /></w:trPr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Category</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Outlier hours (h/week)</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">40, 30, 10, 8, 7, 7, 6.5, 6, 5.5, 5, 5, 4.5, 4, 3.5, 3.2, 3, 3, 3, 3, 3, 3, 3</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">In-service Teachers</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">443, 54, 30, 20, 10, 9, 8.5</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr><w:tr><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Pre-service Teachers</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc><w:tc><w:tcPr /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:jc w:val="left" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">44, 8, 7, 5</w:t></w:r></w:p></w:tc></w:tr></w:tbl><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="CaptionedFigure" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:drawing><wp:inline><wp:extent cx="4389120" cy="2903065" /><wp:effectExtent b="0" l="0" r="0" t="0" /><wp:docPr descr="Figure 3. AI usage for study/teaching by participant category." title="" id="47" name="Picture" /><a:graphic><a:graphicData uri="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/picture"><pic:pic><pic:nvPicPr><pic:cNvPr descr="assets/figures/study_ai_usage.png" id="48" name="Picture" /><pic:cNvPicPr><a:picLocks noChangeArrowheads="1" noChangeAspect="1" /></pic:cNvPicPr></pic:nvPicPr><pic:blipFill><a:blip r:embed="rId46" /><a:stretch><a:fillRect /></a:stretch></pic:blipFill><pic:spPr bwMode="auto"><a:xfrm><a:off x="0" y="0" /><a:ext cx="4389120" cy="2903065" /></a:xfrm><a:prstGeom prst="rect"><a:avLst /></a:prstGeom><a:noFill /><a:ln w="9525"><a:noFill /><a:headEnd /><a:tailEnd /></a:ln></pic:spPr></pic:pic></a:graphicData></a:graphic></wp:inline></w:drawing></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="ImageCaption" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Figure 3. AI usage for study/teaching by participant category.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Figure 3 shows that educational use follows the same hierarchy: 74.8% of students (202/270) employ AI to support their studies, while only 45.2% of in-service teachers (161/356) integrate it into teaching and 28.3% of pre-service teachers (28/99) do so.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="49" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="50" w:name="tools-employed" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.3.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Tools Employed</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A critical finding concerns the concentration of AI experience around a single platform. Both students and teachers utilize a limited number of AI tools, with overwhelming predominance of ChatGPT. This monoculture in tool adoption means that users’ AI experience is confined to a single generalist platform, without exploring more specific tools designed explicitly for educational contexts, such as:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1006" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">NotebookLM (for research and note-taking support)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1006" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Specialized tutoring systems</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1006" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Subject-specific AI assistants</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1006" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Tools designed for lesson planning and assessment creation</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This narrow tool repertoire prevents users from developing articulated understanding of different AI applications and their specific educational affordances, limiting the perceived and actual utility of AI in education.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="50" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="51" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="54" w:name="perceived-competence" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived Competence</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">One of the most revealing findings concerns the significant gap between perceived practical and theoretical competence, particularly pronounced among students.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="52" w:name="student-competence-perceptions" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.4.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Student Competence Perceptions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students’ self-assessed practical competence shows a mean of 4.32 (median = 4) on the 7-point scale, while theoretical competence averages only 3.16 (median = 3). This gap of over one point on the Likert scale indicates substantial discrepancy between operational know-how and understanding of underlying principles.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The distribution of student responses illuminates this pattern more clearly:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1007" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Practical competence</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Seventy students rated themselves at 5, and forty-nine at 6, creating a critical mass of students who perceive themselves as confidently competent in practical AI tool usage.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1007" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Theoretical competence</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Conversely, concentration clusters at lower values—eighty-three responses at 2 and fifty-two at 3—indicating limited formal understanding.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This pattern configures a predominantly empirical learning model based on trial and error. Students acquire operational mastery through direct experimentation without developing formal understanding of:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- How AI systems process and generate responses</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- What biases and limitations these systems contain</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Epistemological boundaries of AI-generated knowledge</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Methods for critically validating AI outputs</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">However, this informal learning approach should not be dismissed as inherently problematic. As Jenkins and collaborators have demonstrated in their work on participatory culture and media literacy</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Jenkins et al., 2009, 2015)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, informal peer-driven learning can be highly effective for developing practical competencies, fostering creativity, and building collaborative knowledge communities. Students’ enthusiastic adoption of AI tools represents valuable agency and resourcefulness—evidence of learners actively responding to new technological affordances and developing competencies through authentic use contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The challenge is not that informal learning is occurring, but rather that educational institutions have largely failed to engage with and build upon these emergent practices. Instead of capitalizing on students’ enthusiasm and practical experience as a foundation for deeper critical engagement, many institutions have responded with prohibitive approaches that frame AI use primarily as a new form of academic dishonesty. This reactive stance misses the opportunity to channel students’ genuine interest and developing skills toward more sophisticated digital literacy.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Rather than penalizing AI use as mere copying or cheating, educational institutions should navigate and harness this enthusiasm, providing the critical frameworks, theoretical depth, and ethical scaffolding that would transform practical competence into genuine AI literacy. The goal should be building upon the valuable informal learning already occurring while addressing its limitations through complementary formal engagement.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="52" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="53" w:name="teacher-competence-perceptions" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.4.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teacher Competence Perceptions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers present a different but equally concerning pattern. Practical competence averages 3.74, while theoretical competence reaches 3.28. Although the gap between dimensions is smaller than for students, both values remain below the scale midpoint, signaling general perceived inadequacy.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Particularly significant: eighty-two teachers out of 358 rated themselves at 2 for practical competence. A considerable portion of the teaching body feels inadequate in practically using the very tools they should be able to teach students to employ critically and consciously.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This finding is unsurprising given the barriers previously analyzed but raises critical questions about how to adequately prepare educators for pedagogical AI integration. Teachers find themselves in a paradoxical position: expected to guide students toward responsible AI use while lacking confidence in their own competencies.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="53" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="54" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="55" w:name="training-adequacy" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Training Adequacy</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perhaps the most alarming finding concerns evaluation of formal AI training received. Students assign a mean rating of 3.3, while teachers report 2.93—both significantly below the scale midpoint, indicating widespread dissatisfaction.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The response distribution is revealing and concerning:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: 22% assigned the minimum value, judging training</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">not at all adequate</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: 28% assigned the minimum value</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This negative perception becomes even more critical when related to actual usage data: 80% of students use AI daily, yet the majority consider their formal training inadequate.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This configuration reveals a scenario where competency acquisition occurs primarily through informal channels—peer knowledge sharing, experiential exploration, and community-driven learning. While such informal learning has proven valuable in digital contexts, as documented by Jenkins and others in studies of participatory culture</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Jenkins et al., 2009, 2015)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, the complete absence of complementary formal education creates significant risks:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1008" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Unbalanced development</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Practical skills develop without the theoretical foundations that enable deeper understanding of AI mechanisms, limitations, and appropriate contexts for use.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1008" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Missing critical frameworks</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Informal peer learning excels at sharing techniques but typically lacks structured approaches to critical evaluation, bias recognition, and epistemological questioning.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1008" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Ethical gaps</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Without formal institutional engagement, users remain unprepared to recognize and address complex ethical issues (bias, privacy, intellectual property, equity concerns).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1008" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Unrealized synergy</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: The educational system faces an evident institutional failure—not because informal learning is inadequate, but because schools have failed to build upon and enrich these emergent practices with the pedagogical frameworks, critical scaffolding, and methodological depth that should constitute formal education’s complementary value.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The problem is not informal learning itself, but rather the absence of formal institutional engagement to deepen, contextualize, and critically frame the practical competencies students are developing. The discrepancy between intensive use and institutional absence constitutes one of the most urgent challenges for conscious and responsible AI integration in education.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="55" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="58" w:name="perceived-impact-and-change" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived Impact and Change</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Analysis of perceptions regarding AI’s transformative impact reveals a psychologically significant pattern, particularly among teachers.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="56" w:name="the-third-person-bias-among-teachers" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.6.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Third-Person Bias Among Teachers</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">When asked how much AI will change teaching in general, teachers respond decisively positively: mean = 5.45, median = 6, indicating widespread recognition of the technology’s transformative potential in education.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">However, when the question becomes personal—</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">How much will it change YOUR way of teaching?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">—values drop to mean = 4.68, median = 5. This gap of nearly 0.8 points is both statistically significant and psychologically revealing.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This phenomenon constitutes what the literature terms</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">third-person bias</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Davison, 1983; Paul et al., 2000; Perloff, 1999)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: the tendency to believe that major changes will affect others more than oneself. This can be interpreted through two complementary lenses:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1009" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Psychological defense mechanism</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: A protective response to change perceived as destabilizing to established professional practices and identity.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1009" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Pragmatic uncertainty</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Concrete doubt about how to effectively integrate AI into one’s daily teaching practice, highlighting the distance between theoretical recognition of AI’s potential and practical capacity to incorporate it into one’s pedagogical repertoire.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="56" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="57" w:name="student-impact-expectations" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.6.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Student Impact Expectations</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students show more moderate expectations regarding change to their study approaches, with mean = 4.91. While recognizing that AI will impact their learning modalities, they do not perceive it as revolutionary to the same extent that teachers predict its impact on teaching.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This difference in perception may suggest that students, already immersed in daily technology use, maintain a more pragmatic and less idealized view compared to teachers. Their familiarity with AI tools tempers expectations, while teachers—many of whom have limited direct experience—may simultaneously overestimate general impact while underestimating personal implications.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="57" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="58" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="62" w:name="trust-and-concerns" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.7</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust and Concerns</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">One of the most significant findings concerns trust in AI integration and concerns about responsible use.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="59" w:name="trust-in-ai-integration" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.7.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust in AI Integration</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students express trust in AI integration with mean = 4.47 (median = 5), while teachers report lower levels: mean = 4.12 (median = 4).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This asymmetry is notable: those who will be guided in technology use demonstrate greater optimism than those who must provide guidance. This divergence can be interpreted through several factors:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1010" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Generational technological familiarity</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Younger generations’ greater familiarity with digital technologies makes them naturally more inclined to embrace innovations with confidence.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1010" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Pedagogical awareness</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Teachers’ concerns reflect deeper awareness of complexities involved in didactic AI integration—aspects that students may not perceive or may underestimate.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1010" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Responsibility burden</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Teachers bear professional responsibility for educational outcomes, naturally increasing caution about adopting potentially disruptive technologies.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="59" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="60" w:name="teachers-concerns-about-student-ai-use" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.7.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers’ Concerns About Student AI Use</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Even more significant is data regarding teachers’ trust in students’ capacity for conscious and critical AI use. Teachers’ concerns about student AI usage show mean = 4.71, with nearly 60% of responses concentrated at high scale values.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Educators clearly harbor substantial doubts about students’ critical capacity to employ these tools reflectively and appropriately. This concern likely stems from:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1011" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Observed instances of uncritical AI dependence</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1011" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Cases of academic dishonesty or inappropriate AI use</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1011" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Recognition of the competence gap revealed in this study</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1011" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">General anxiety about students’ critical thinking development</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="60" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="61" w:name="the-educational-paradox" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.7.3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Educational Paradox</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Synthesis of these data composes a problematic picture: 80% of students use AI daily, while teachers express concern and distrust toward their capacity to do so consciously. A paradoxical situation emerges, comparable to numerous drivers operating without licenses, under the worried gaze of instructors lacking adequate tools to intervene effectively.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This misalignment between intensive use and lack of guided critical competencies represents one of the most urgent criticalities to address for ensuring responsible and pedagogically grounded AI integration in education.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Significantly, students themselves are aware of this inadequacy, as demonstrated by their negative evaluation of teachers’ AI preparation (median = 3 on the question</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">How prepared do you think your teachers are about AI?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">). This mutual awareness of unpreparedness—teachers recognize their limitations, students recognize their teachers’ limitations—underscores the urgent need for systematic institutional intervention.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="61" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="62" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="63" w:name="student-specific-perceptions" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6.8</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Student-Specific Perceptions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Analysis of questions directed specifically at students reveals an articulated picture of their AI perceptions in educational contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Q1: Impact on study methods</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Mean = 4.91, Median = 5)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Students express elevated expectations, with distribution concentrated on medium-high scale values. They recognize that AI will represent a significant transformative element in their learning modalities, while maintaining a substantially balanced and not excessively enthusiastic attitude.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Q2: Teacher preparedness on AI</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Median = 3)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A particularly critical finding emerges from students’ evaluation of their teachers’ AI preparation. The median at value 3, with significant response concentration at low scale values, indicates clear student perception of teaching body’s formative inadequacy. Students recognize a competence gap, confirming what emerged from teachers’ own responses. This awareness is significant: students not only use technology intensively but can also critically evaluate limitations of those who should guide them in its use.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Q3: Concern about AI use in schools generally</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Median ≈ 3)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Concern for AI use in education generally shows moderate values, suggesting a cautious but not alarmed attitude.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Q4: Concern about peers’ AI use</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Median ≈ 3)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Similarly, concern about classmates’ AI usage remains moderate, indicating that while students recognize potential criticalities, they do not experience technology integration as a substantial threat.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This relative tranquility contrasts with teachers’ more marked concerns, delineating a generational difference in emotional and value-based approach to technology that merits particular attention in AI integration strategies.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="63" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="64" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="72" w:name="discussion" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Discussion</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="65" w:name="Xca4f0d877dc0bdba4c7f16fe390e5e94ba8c0f0" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Massive Adoption Without Institutional Engagement</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The first element emerging forcefully is the presence of massive but profoundly uneven AI adoption. Eighty percent of students use these tools daily, configuring a practice now consolidated and rooted in their study routines. This represents remarkable student initiative and adaptability—evidence of learners taking agency in their educational practices and responding to technological opportunities. However, this student-driven adoption has occurred in an institutional vacuum, without the complementary engagement that would maximize educational potential and mitigate risks.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Monoculture and Tool Concentration</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Usage experience concentrates almost exclusively on ChatGPT, with substantial ignorance of more specific and pedagogically oriented tools. This technological monoculture prevents students from developing articulated understanding of different AI applications and their specific educational potentials. Students learn to interact with a single conversational interface without exploring:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1012" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Specialized research assistants with citation tracking</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1012" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Subject-specific tutoring systems designed with pedagogical scaffolding</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1012" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Tools for collaborative learning and peer feedback</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1012" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Assessment and formative feedback platforms</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1012" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Multimodal learning environments combining text, audio, and visual AI capabilities</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Usage Polarization</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A sharp polarization exists between occasional users (one to two hours weekly) and power users demonstrating intensive usage. This fragmentation reflects the nature of informal, peer-driven adoption—where individual discovery and personal networks shape learning trajectories rather than systematic institutional guidance.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This pattern reveals that while AI has penetrated educational practices through bottom-up student initiative, formal education has failed to engage. Schools and universities have largely remained passive observers of a student-driven transformation rather than active partners who could enrich these emergent practices with critical frameworks, broaden tool awareness, and support development from practical competence to sophisticated literacy.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="65" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="66" w:name="X3b6d852ddbf7ab4127b468b595980172a6908b1" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Competence Paradox: Knowing How Without Understanding Why</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">One of the most significant results concerns the gap between practical and theoretical competence, particularly marked among students. The capacity to use tools (mean = 4.32) exceeds understanding of underlying principles (mean = 3.16) by over one point.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This gap configures a learning model based on trial and error, where operational skill acquisition occurs empirically and unstructured, without passing through formal understanding of mechanisms, logic, and technology limitations.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Implications of Surface-Level Literacy</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Such an approach, while enabling rapid tool familiarization, precludes development of critical and metacognitive competencies indispensable for conscious and responsible AI use. Students know how to query a GenAI system but don’t understand:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1013" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">How it processes information and generates responses</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1013" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">What biases it may contain and how these arise</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1013" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">What epistemological limits it presents</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1013" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">How to validate AI output critically</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1013" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">When AI use is appropriate versus when human cognition is essential</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1013" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">What ethical considerations govern responsible use</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This constitutes superficial technological literacy risking production of uncritical users rather than competent digital citizens. The parallel to functional illiteracy is apt: just as functionally illiterate individuals can decode text without comprehending meaning, these students can operate AI tools without understanding their operation, limitations, or appropriate contexts for use.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Professional Preparation Crisis</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers present a different but equally concerning pattern. Both practical (3.74) and theoretical (3.28) competence remain below scale midpoint, signaling general perceived inadequacy. Eighty-two teachers rated themselves at 2 for practical competence—a considerable teaching body portion feeling inadequate in practically using the very tools they should teach students to employ critically.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This creates a dangerous educational vacuum: students use AI intensively without critical frameworks, while teachers lack confidence and competence to provide necessary guidance. The traditional model of educator as informed guide breaks down when educators feel less competent than their students.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="66" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="67" w:name="the-institutional-training-void" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7.3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Institutional Training Void</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perhaps the most alarming finding concerns training adequacy evaluation. Both students (mean = 3.3) and teachers (mean = 2.93) express significantly negative judgments, with over a quarter of teachers considering it</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">not at all adequate.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Practice-Training Imbalance</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This judgment assumes dramatic contours when considered in relation to daily technology use: students are actively learning through practice, but formal education has withdrawn from engagement rather than building upon these emergent practices. The educational system faces an evident institutional void. While students develop AI competencies through informal peer-to-peer channels—leveraging the kinds of participatory learning networks that Jenkins and others have documented as powerful sites of knowledge construction</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Jenkins, 2006; Jenkins et al., 2009, 2015)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">—educational institutions have failed to recognize and engage with these learning ecosystems, missing the opportunity to provide the critical frameworks, theoretical depth, and ethical scaffolding that would constitute formal education’s complementary value.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Strengths and Limitations of Informal AI Learning</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The learning occurs through valuable but incomplete channels:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Peer sharing of prompts and techniques (effective for practical knowledge transfer)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Trial-and-error experimentation (builds operational competence)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Imitation of observed practices (enables rapid skill acquisition)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- YouTube tutorials and online communities (accessible learning resources)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Incidental discovery through use (experiential learning)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">These informal learning mechanisms demonstrate significant strengths: they are accessible, responsive to learner needs, embedded in authentic contexts, and driven by intrinsic motivation. Research on participatory culture and connected learning has shown that such peer-driven knowledge networks can be highly effective for developing practical competencies</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Jenkins, 2009; Jenkins et al., 2015)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">However, without complementary formal engagement, this learning ecosystem produces unbalanced development. While practical skills flourish, critical dimensions remain underdeveloped: systematic understanding of AI mechanisms and limitations, frameworks for evaluating bias and reliability, ethical reasoning about appropriate use contexts, awareness of privacy and intellectual property implications, and metacognitive reflection on how AI use affects one’s own thinking and learning processes.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The problem is not the informal learning itself—which represents valuable student agency and resourcefulness—but rather the institutional failure to engage with and build upon these emergent practices.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Understanding the Student-Teacher Usage Gap</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The substantial disparity in AI adoption between students (80% daily use) and teachers (57% for in-service, 51.5% for pre-service teachers) reflects multiple converging factors beyond mere technological access:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1014" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Accessibility and immediacy</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: AI tools prove more immediately accessible and useful for students, who can obtain quick explanations, homework support, and study assistance through simple conversational interfaces. The lower barriers to entry for student use cases—straightforward question-answering and content generation—contrast sharply with the more complex professional integration required for teaching.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1014" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Professional complexity</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Teachers face more complex integration challenges. Their professional needs require targeted, structured resources that align with curricular objectives, pedagogical frameworks, and assessment criteria. The accumulated experience of teachers allows them to draw upon extensive traditional materials that, in the current phase, often prove more reliable and pedagogically appropriate than generic AI outputs. Integrating AI into teaching practice demands not merely tool competence but pedagogical redesign—understanding how AI can complement rather than replace human instruction, how to scaffold student use ethically, and how to assess learning in AI-mediated contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1014" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Skepticism and caution</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Teachers demonstrate greater skepticism toward an evolving technology, maintaining a prudent waiting stance to better understand its real potentials and limitations in educational contexts. This caution reflects professional responsibility: teachers cannot experiment freely with students’ learning experiences in the way students can with their own study methods. The stakes of pedagogical decisions—affecting student achievement, equity, and development—justify measured evaluation before wholesale adoption.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1014" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Generational factors</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Younger cohorts demonstrate greater propensity for adopting new technologies and a more exploratory attitude toward experimentation. Students integrate digital tools into their daily routines with naturalness, contrasting with the caution and skepticism often characterizing teacher approaches. This generational dimension intersects with the previous factors, as digital nativity shapes both comfort with new interfaces and willingness to tolerate ambiguity during exploratory learning.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Self-Directed Learning Paradox</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perhaps most paradoxical is the finding regarding autonomous learning effort. Both students and teachers report that formal AI training is grossly inadequate (students mean = 3.3, teachers mean = 2.93), yet autonomous engagement with AI training remains remarkably low across both groups. The data reveal median self-directed AI learning time close to zero for students (median = 0 hours, Q1–Q3 = 0–1 hours) and only marginally higher for teachers (median = 1 hour, Q1–Q3 = 0–2 hours).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Notably, while both groups demonstrate low engagement, students show slightly more autonomous learning activity than teachers—with a longer right tail of intensive learners investing 40+ hours weekly in self-education about AI tools. This pattern suggests that while most participants remain passive consumers waiting for institutional training, a minority—predominantly younger learners—actively construct their own learning pathways.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This creates a troubling circularity: participants critique institutional training as inadequate, yet do not compensate through autonomous professional development. The expectation that institutions should provide comprehensive training coexists with minimal personal investment in self-directed learning. This phenomenon may reflect several dynamics:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1015" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Learned passivity</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Educational systems have conditioned participants to expect formal instruction rather than cultivate autonomous learning dispositions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1015" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Lack of meta-learning competence</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Participants may lack the metacognitive skills and information literacy necessary to identify quality learning resources and structure effective self-directed learning</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1015" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perceived futility</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Without institutional validation and integration, self-acquired competencies may seem professionally irrelevant</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1015" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Temporal constraints</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Both students and teachers face demanding schedules, relegating non-mandatory learning to low priority</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This paradox connects directly to the training adequacy crisis: the combination of inadequate institutional support and limited autonomous learning creates a competence vacuum. Participants recognize their insufficient preparation yet remain largely passive in addressing it, waiting for institutions that have thus far failed to respond.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The bimodal usage pattern documented earlier—occasional users versus power users—thus reflects not merely different adoption levels but fundamentally different approaches to learning and professional development. Power users, while still a minority, demonstrate the kind of agency and self-directed learning that would ideally characterize professional educators. The question becomes: how can institutions catalyze this minority pattern into majority practice, transforming passive expectation into active engagement while simultaneously providing the formal frameworks that self-directed learning alone cannot supply?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="67" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="68" w:name="Xf3b14264537fe4b3c078d3775a49bdd0b012fb3" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7.4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Third-Person Bias and Resistance to Change</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers manifest an interesting psychological phenomenon: while recognizing that AI will significantly change teaching generally (mean = 5.45), they are much more cautious in predicting impact on their own personal didactic practice (mean = 4.68).</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">third-person bias</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">can be interpreted as:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1016" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Psychological defense mechanism</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Protection against change perceived as destabilizing to professional identity and established practices. After years or decades developing particular pedagogical approaches, the prospect of fundamental transformation provokes anxiety and resistance.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1016" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Pragmatic uncertainty</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Concrete doubt about how to translate theoretical recognition of AI potential into effective didactic practices. Teachers may genuinely want to integrate AI but lack clear models, examples, and support structures for doing so.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1016" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Professional conservatism</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Understandable hesitation to abandon proven methods for untested technologies, particularly given responsibility for student learning outcomes.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Competence and Change Readiness</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This phenomenon accompanies generally low perceived competence levels (practical mean = 3.74) and a significant mass of teachers at lowest scale values. A teaching body emerges feeling inadequate regarding tools they should be able to teach critical use of, trapped between recognizing technology relevance and incapacity to integrate it effectively into professional practice.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This situation generates professional stress and cognitive dissonance: teachers recognize they should adapt but don’t know how, creating anxiety, frustration, and sometimes defensive rejection of the technology.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="68" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="69" w:name="X0afe2932420829bee4ef3565b6b6fda4080ff22" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7.5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Trust Paradox: Guides Who Distrust Those They Guide</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">A further critical element concerns trust asymmetry. Students demonstrate greater confidence in AI integration in education (mean = 4.47) than teachers (mean = 4.12), configuring an asymmetry where those who should be guided are more optimistic than those who should guide.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teachers’ Concerns About Student Use</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">More worrying is teacher trust data regarding students’ critical capacity: concerns reach high values (mean = 4.71), with nearly 60% of responses concentrated at high scale values.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">An educational paradox emerges: 80% of students use AI daily, while teachers distrust their capacity to do so consciously and critically, yet simultaneously don’t possess formative tools and necessary competencies to intervene effectively.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Unlicensed Driver Metaphor</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">It’s as if numerous drivers operate without licenses under worried instructor gazes who lack means to teach proper driving. This metaphor captures several dimensions:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1017" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Ubiquitous unsupervised practice</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Students use AI extensively without proper training or oversight</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1017" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Recognized incompetence</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Both teachers and students acknowledge the lack of adequate preparation</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1017" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Inability to intervene</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Teachers lack confidence and tools to provide needed guidance</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1017" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Accident risk</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: The potential for serious negative consequences (academic dishonesty, skill atrophy, uncritical acceptance of biased or incorrect information)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Significantly, students themselves recognize this inadequacy, as demonstrated by negative evaluation of teacher AI preparation (median = 3). This creates a situation of mutual acknowledged incompetence that is both unusual and problematic in educational contexts.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="69" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="70" w:name="X2293d988ca4e830abcdbbfc0fc60340d4a24e73" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7.6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Broader Implications for Educational Theory and Practice</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">These findings intersect with several important theoretical frameworks:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Social Cognitive Theory and Self-Efficacy</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The competence-confidence gap illuminates Bandura’s concept of self-efficacy</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Bandura, 1977, 1986)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Students demonstrate high self-efficacy for practical AI use but lack the mastery experiences and vicarious learning that would build self-efficacy for critical evaluation</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Honicke &amp; Broadbent, 2016)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Teachers show low self-efficacy across both dimensions, potentially creating a self-fulfilling prophecy where anxiety prevents the engagement necessary to build genuine competence.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Technology Acceptance Models</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Classical technology acceptance models emphasize perceived usefulness and ease of use as adoption drivers</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Davis, 1989; Venkatesh et al., 2003; Venkatesh &amp; Davis, 2000)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Our findings suggest these factors operate differently for students and teachers. For students, immediate usefulness (homework help, quick answers) and ease of use (conversational interface) drive rapid adoption despite inadequate understanding. For teachers, professional complexity and pedagogical responsibility create higher thresholds for perceived usefulness, while lower confidence reduces perceived ease of use.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Sociocultural Learning Theory</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Vygotsky’s emphasis on mediated learning and the zone of proximal development highlights the problematic nature of unguided AI adoption. Students operate within their current capability zone but lack expert guidance to extend into new zones of understanding. The absence of knowledgeable others capable of providing appropriate scaffolding limits development of sophisticated AI literacy.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Critical Digital Literacy</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Our findings underscore the urgent need for critical digital literacy frameworks that extend beyond operational skills to encompass</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Carretero et al., 2017; Vuorikari et al., 2016)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Understanding of sociotechnical systems and their embedded values</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Recognition of algorithmic bias and its sources</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Evaluation of information credibility and AI output reliability</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Ethical reasoning about appropriate use contexts</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Metacognitive awareness of how AI use affects one’s own thinking</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="70" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="71" w:name="the-urgency-of-systematic-intervention" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">7.7</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Urgency of Systematic Intervention</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">These data, in their totality, delineate an educational urgency that cannot be further ignored or postponed. AI integration in educational contexts is occurring de facto, but chaotically, unguidedly, and pedagogically inadequately.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Systematic and structured intervention is necessary, simultaneously addressing multiple dimensions:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">1. Teacher Professional Development</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Investment in serious and continuous teacher training pathways is indispensable, moving beyond operational tool use to develop:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Critical understanding of AI fundamentals (not computer science depth, but sufficient conceptual understanding)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Pedagogical implications and integration strategies</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Ethical frameworks for responsible use</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Practical experience with diverse AI applications</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Confidence through supported experimentation and community of practice development</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">2. Structured Student Curricula</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Building upon and enriching the informal learning already occurring requires introducing curricular pathways that combine:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Practical competence with varied tools and contexts</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Theoretical understanding of AI capabilities and limitations</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Critical literacy for output evaluation</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Ethical reasoning about appropriate use</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Metacognitive awareness of AI’s effects on learning and thinking</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">3. Tool Diversification</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Promoting knowledge and use of tools specifically designed for educational contexts, overcoming exclusive dependence on generalist platforms like ChatGPT. This includes:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Subject-specific tutoring systems</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Research and citation support tools</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Collaborative learning platforms</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Formative assessment and feedback tools</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Specialized applications for different learning needs and contexts</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">4. Pedagogical Research</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Developing empirical research on:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Most effective AI integration modalities in didactics</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Effects on learning outcomes, engagement, and skill development</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Strategies for preventing uncritical and superficial use</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Assessment approaches that account for AI availability</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Longitudinal impacts on cognitive development and learning dispositions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">5. Rethinking Didactic Practices</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Supporting teachers in rethinking their practices in light of AI-offered possibilities, overcoming both defensive attitudes and uncritical enthusiasm to develop pedagogically grounded and critically conscious approaches. This includes:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Redesigning assignments and assessments to be AI-aware</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Developing pedagogies that leverage AI for enhanced learning</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Creating classroom cultures of critical AI engagement</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Modeling thoughtful AI use and limitations acknowledgment</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">6. Institutional Policy and Infrastructure</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Developing clear institutional policies and support structures:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Guidelines for appropriate and inappropriate AI use in different contexts</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Infrastructure supporting responsible AI access and use</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Mechanisms for ongoing policy review as technology evolves</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Resources for sustained professional development and curricular innovation</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:r><w:pict><v:rect style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t" /></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="71" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="72" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="73" w:name="conclusion" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Conclusion</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">We stand at a critical juncture in educational technology integration. The findings of this study reveal a significant and troubling gap between the rapid, widespread adoption of GenAI by students and the capacity of educational institutions to provide appropriate guidance, critical frameworks, and pedagogical support.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Current State: A Perfect Storm of Challenges</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The data compose a picture of:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Massive adoption without institutional engagement</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: 80% of students using AI daily through valuable informal peer-driven channels, but without complementary formal support</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Competence imbalance</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: High operational skills but low theoretical understanding and critical literacy—practical knowledge flourishing while critical frameworks remain absent</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Institutional withdrawal</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Widespread dissatisfaction with formal AI training among both students and teachers, reflecting failure to engage with emergent learning practices</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teacher unpreparedness</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Educators feeling inadequate to guide students in tools they should be teaching critical use of</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust asymmetry</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Students more confident than teachers, while teachers distrust students’ critical capacity</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Limited tool awareness</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Concentration around single generalist platform, missing specialized educational applications</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">-</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Resistance and uncertainty</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Teachers recognizing AI’s transformative potential generally while uncertain about personal integration</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This configuration presents both urgent risks and significant opportunities.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Risks of Inaction</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">If we allow AI to integrate into educational contexts spontaneously and disorderedly, we face serious risks:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1018" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Erosion of critical thinking</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Uncritical reliance on AI outputs without developing capacity to evaluate, question, and verify</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1018" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Cognitive skill atrophy</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Outsourcing thinking processes that are essential for deep learning and intellectual development</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1018" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perpetuation of biases</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Uncritical acceptance of biased AI outputs reinforcing existing inequalities and misconceptions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1018" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Academic integrity crisis</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Difficulty distinguishing authentic student work from AI-generated content</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1018" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Widening divides</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Growing gaps between students with access to AI guidance and those without</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1018" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Professional teacher demoralization</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Increasing educator stress, inadequacy feelings, and potential exodus from profession</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Opportunities for Thoughtful Integration</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Conversely, with systematic intervention, we can realize AI’s genuine educational potential:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1019" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Personalized learning support</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: AI as tutor providing customized explanations, practice, and feedback at scale</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1019" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Accessibility enhancement</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Support for diverse learners including those with disabilities, language learners, and students in under-resourced contexts</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1019" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teacher empowerment</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: AI handling routine tasks, enabling teachers to focus on relationship-building, complex instruction, and individual support</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1019" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Creativity and exploration</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: AI as collaborative partner in creative projects, idea generation, and exploratory learning</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1019" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Development of new literacies</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Building critical AI literacy as essential 21st-century competence</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Compact" /><w:numPr><w:ilvl w:val="0" /><w:numId w:val="1019" /></w:numPr></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Research and innovation acceleration</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Using AI tools to advance educational research and develop innovative pedagogical approaches</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Path Forward: Building a Pedagogy of AI</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Moving from current challenges to realized opportunities requires building what we term a</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">pedagogy of AI</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">—a comprehensive approach encompassing:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Foundational principles:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- AI as tool requiring critical engagement, not autonomous authority</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Transparency about AI use, capabilities, and limitations</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Emphasis on human judgment, creativity, and ethical reasoning</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Focus on learning processes, not just products</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Commitment to equity and inclusion in AI access and literacy</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Practical components:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Comprehensive teacher professional development</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Integrated student curricula building critical AI literacy</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Clear institutional policies and ethical frameworks</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Ongoing research informing evidence-based practice</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Community engagement involving all educational stakeholders</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Cultural transformation:</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Shifting from fear-based prohibition to critical engagement</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Embracing experimentation within ethical boundaries</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Developing shared norms and practices across institutions</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Building cultures of transparency and continuous learning</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">- Recognizing AI integration as ongoing process, not one-time event</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">The Decisive Moment</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The data tell us unequivocally that we are at a bifurcation point. One path—continuing institutional absence—allows the current imbalance to persist, where valuable informal learning occurs without the complementary formal engagement necessary to develop critical literacy, theoretical depth, and ethical sophistication. The other path requires conscious, active institutional commitment to engaging with and building upon students’ emergent practices, providing the pedagogical frameworks, professional capacities, and critical literacies necessary to realize AI’s educational potential while mitigating its risks.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The choice is not whether AI will be part of education—that decision has already been made by students who have integrated it into their daily practices through their own agency and initiative. The choice is whether we, as educators, researchers, and institutional leaders, will play an active role as partners in shaping that integration toward educational purposes and critical engagement, or whether we will remain passive observers of a transformation happening without our participation.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">A Call to Action</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">This study issues an urgent call to action for all educational stakeholders:</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">To policymakers</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Invest in comprehensive AI literacy initiatives, support teacher professional development, and develop thoughtful regulatory frameworks balancing innovation with protection.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">To educational institutions</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Move beyond reactive prohibition to proactive pedagogy, developing clear policies, support structures, and curricular innovations that embrace AI critically.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">To teacher educators</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Integrate AI literacy into pre-service and in-service teacher preparation, modeling thoughtful engagement and building educator confidence.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">To researchers</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Conduct rigorous empirical studies examining AI’s educational impacts, effective integration strategies, and long-term consequences for learning and development.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">To teachers</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Engage courageously with AI despite uncertainty, seeking support, experimenting within ethical bounds, and contributing to emerging communities of practice.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">To students</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Advocate for the guidance you deserve, engage critically with AI tools you use, and recognize that superficial competence differs fundamentally from deep literacy.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The construction of a genuine</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">“</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">pedagogy of artificial intelligence</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">”</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">is no longer optional—it is an educational imperative. Only through systematic, thoughtful, evidence-based intervention can we ensure that this powerful technology becomes an authentic tool for enriching educational experience rather than a factor impoverishing critical thought and students’ intellectual autonomy.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">The moment for decision is now. The data have spoken. The path forward requires courage, commitment, and collective action. Our students—and the future of education—deserve nothing less.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:r><w:pict><v:rect style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t" /></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="73" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="88" w:name="appendix-survey-questions" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Appendix: Survey Questions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="80" w:name="student-questionnaire" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Student Questionnaire</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="74" w:name="demographic-questions" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.1.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Demographic Questions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quanti anni hai?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: How old are you?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Numeric)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Il tuo genere è</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Your gender is</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Che scuola frequenti</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: What school do you attend?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Titolo di studio</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Educational qualification</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#7</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Il tuo percorso attuale di studio è di tipo</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Your current study path is</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice: STEM or Humanities)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="74" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="75" w:name="usage-pattern-questions-yesno" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.1.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Usage Pattern Questions (Yes/No)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#16</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Nella tua vita quotidiana utilizzi l’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: In your daily life, do you use artificial intelligence?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#19</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Utilizzi l’intelligenza artificiale nello studio?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Do you use artificial intelligence in your studies?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="75" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="76" w:name="usage-pattern-questions-numeric" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.1.3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Usage Pattern Questions (Numeric)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#17</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Se sì, quante ore alla settimana, in media, utilizzi strumenti di intelligenza artificiale per le tue attività quotidiane?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: If yes, how many hours per week on average do you use AI tools for your daily activities?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#20</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quante ore alla settimana mediamente utilizzi l’intelligenza artificiale per le tue attività quotidiane?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: How many hours per week on average do you use AI for your daily activities?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#21</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quante ore alla settimana mediamente utilizzi l’intelligenza artificiale per le attività riguardanti lo studio?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: How many hours per week on average do you use AI for study-related activities?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#22</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quante ore alla settimana mediamente dedichi ad informarti sui nuovi strumenti di intelligenza artificiale per lo studio?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: How many hours per week on average do you dedicate to learning about new AI tools for studying?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#23</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Sapresti quante ore ti fa risparmiare l’uso dell’intelligenza artificiale nel tuo studio in una settimana?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Can you estimate how many hours using AI saves you in your studies per week?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="76" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="77" w:name="X438156260925e13be3482cf9eef10d878c4cbc9" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.1.4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Competence and Training (7-point Likert Scale)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#8</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Su una scala da 1 a 7, quanto ti consideri competente nell’uso pratico di strumenti o tecnologie legati all’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how competent do you consider yourself in the practical use of AI tools or technologies?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#9</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Su una scala da 1 a 7, quanto ritieni adeguata la tua competenza teorica riguardo l’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how adequate do you consider your theoretical competence regarding AI?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#11</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Su una scala da 1 a 7, quanto ritieni adeguata la formazione ricevuta in merito all’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how adequate do you consider the training you received regarding AI?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#13</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Su una scala da 1 a 7, quanto ritieni che i tuoi attuali insegnanti siano preparati e competenti nell’insegnare l’uso dell’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how prepared and competent do you consider your current teachers in teaching AI use?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="77" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="78" w:name="Xd693888938b436d57e2a2f0ec213b41dba68301" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.1.5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust, Confidence, and Concerns (7-point Likert Scale)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#10</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto pensi che l’intelligenza artificiale cambierà il tuo modo di studiare?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how much do you think AI will change your way of studying?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#12</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto sei fiducioso nell’integrazione dell’intelligenza artificiale nella scuola o università?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how confident are you in the integration of AI in school or university?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#14</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, ti preoccupa l’inserimento dell’intelligenza artificiale nella scuola o nell’università?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, does the introduction of AI in school or university concern you?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#15</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto sei preoccupato riguardo all’utilizzo dell’intelligenza artificiale da parte dei tuoi compagni di scuola o universitari?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how concerned are you about the use of AI by your classmates or university peers?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="78" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="79" w:name="multiple-choice-questions" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.1.6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Multiple Choice Questions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#24</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quali sono gli strumenti di intelligenza artificiale che utilizzi?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Which AI tools do you use?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#25</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Per quali scopi usi l’intelligenza artificiale nei tuoi studi?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: For what purposes do you use AI in your studies?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#26</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Per quali tipi di attività NON deve essere utilizzata l’intelligenza artificiale per apprendere?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: For what types of activities should AI NOT be used for learning?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#27</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quali strumenti di intelligenza artificiale utilizzi regolarmente nel tuo studio?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Which AI tools do you regularly use in your studies?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#33</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quali difficoltà hai incontrato nell’implementazione di strumenti di IA nella tua pratica di studio?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: What difficulties have you encountered in implementing AI tools in your study practice?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#35</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: In base alla tua esperienza, quali sono i pro e i contro dell’uso dell’intelligenza artificiale nello studio?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Based on your experience, what are the pros and cons of using AI in studying?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:r><w:pict><v:rect style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t" /></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="79" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="80" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="87" w:name="teacher-questionnaire" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading2" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Teacher Questionnaire</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="81" w:name="demographic-questions-1" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.2.1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Demographic Questions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Attualmente insegni o hai intenzione di intraprendere la professione docente?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Do you currently teach or intend to pursue the teaching profession?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quanti anni hai?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: How old are you?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Numeric)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Il tuo genere è</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Your gender is</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Titolo di studio</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Educational qualification</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#7</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: In quale ordine di scuola insegni? O vorresti insegnare?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: In which school level do you teach? Or would you like to teach?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#8</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Insegna (o insegnerà) una materia</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Do you teach (or will you teach) a subject</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Single choice: STEM or Humanities)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#9</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Qual è il tuo settore scientifico-disciplinare attuale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: What is your current scientific-disciplinary sector?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(Multiple choice)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="81" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="82" w:name="usage-pattern-questions-yesno-1" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.2.2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Usage Pattern Questions (Yes/No)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#20</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Nella tua vita quotidiana utilizzi l’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: In your daily life, do you use artificial intelligence?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#23</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Utilizzi l’intelligenza artificiale nella didattica?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Do you use artificial intelligence in teaching?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="82" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="83" w:name="usage-pattern-questions-numeric-1" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.2.3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Usage Pattern Questions (Numeric)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#21</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Se sì, quante ore alla settimana, in media, utilizzi strumenti di intelligenza artificiale per le tue attività quotidiane?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: If yes, how many hours per week on average do you use AI tools for your daily activities?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#24</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quante ore alla settimana mediamente dedichi alla formazione e all’aggiornamento sulle tecnologie di intelligenza artificiale per l’insegnamento?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: How many hours per week on average do you dedicate to training and updating on AI technologies for teaching?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#25</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quante ore alla settimana dedichi mediamente per integrare strumenti di intelligenza artificiale nei tuoi piani di lezione settimanali?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: How many hours per week on average do you dedicate to integrating AI tools into your weekly lesson plans?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="83" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="84" w:name="X5a5799fd9f7e61d94473d9a66c5f9860761f72c" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.2.4</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Competence and Training (7-point Likert Scale)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#10</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Su una scala da 1 a 7, quanto ti consideri competente nell’uso pratico di strumenti o tecnologie legati all’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how competent do you consider yourself in the practical use of AI tools or technologies?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#11</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Su una scala da 1 a 7, quanto ritieni adeguata la tua competenza teorica riguardo l’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how adequate do you consider your theoretical competence regarding AI?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#14</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Su una scala da 1 a 7, quanto ritieni adeguata la formazione ricevuta in merito all’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how adequate do you consider the training you received regarding AI?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="84" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="85" w:name="X3d55f1621aea3b25cf6d51ef7214a90ea3eabe7" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.2.5</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Trust, Confidence, and Concerns (7-point Likert Scale)</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#12</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7 quanto pensi che l’intelligenza artificiale cambierà la didattica?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how much do you think AI will change teaching (in general)?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#13</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto pensi che l’intelligenza artificiale cambierà la tua didattica?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how much do you think AI will change your teaching (personal)?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#15</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto sei fiducioso nell’integrazione dell’intelligenza artificiale nella pratica educativa?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how confident are you in the integration of AI in educational practice?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#16</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto sei fiducioso nell’utilizzo da parte degli studenti di un uso responsabile e maturo dell’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how confident are you in students’ responsible and mature use of AI?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#17</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto sei preoccupato riguardo all’utilizzo dell’intelligenza artificiale nel mondo dell’educazione?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how concerned are you about the use of AI in the world of education?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#18</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Da una scala da 1 a 7, quanto sei preoccupato riguardo all’utilizzo dell’intelligenza artificiale da parte degli studenti?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: On a scale from 1 to 7, how concerned are you about students’ use of AI?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="85" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="86" w:name="multiple-choice-questions-1" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading3" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="SectionNumber" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">8.2.6</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:tab /></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Multiple Choice Questions</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="FirstParagraph" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#19</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Per quali tipi di attività NON deve essere utilizzata l’intelligenza artificiale nell’insegnamento?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: For what types of activities should AI NOT be used in teaching?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#26</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quali sono gli strumenti di intelligenza artificiale che utilizzi?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: Which AI tools do you use?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#27</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Per quali tipi di attività usi l’intelligenza artificiale?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: For what types of activities do you use AI?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="BodyText" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:b /><w:bCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">#34</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">: Quali difficoltà hai incontrato nell’implementazione di strumenti di IA nella tua didattica?</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Translation: What difficulties have you encountered in implementing AI tools in your teaching?</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:p><w:r><w:pict><v:rect style="width:0;height:1.5pt" o:hralign="center" o:hrstd="t" o:hr="t" /></w:pict></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="86" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="87" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="88" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="149" w:name="references" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Heading1" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">References</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkStart w:id="148" w:name="refs" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="90" w:name="ref-Allison2025CommitmentTrust" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Allison, L., &amp; Blair, J. (2025). Extending commitment-trust theory to AI adoption: A multi-study investigation in educational settings.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Marketing Education Review</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, 1–13.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId89"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1080/10528008.2025.2574501</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="90" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="92" w:name="ref-Bandura1977Selfeffic" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Bandura, A. (1977). Self-efficacy: Toward a unifying theory of behavioral change.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Psychological Review</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">84</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(2), 191–215.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId91"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295X.84.2.191</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="92" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="93" w:name="ref-Bandura1986SocialFoun" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Bandura, A. (1986).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Social foundations of thought and action: A social cognitive theory</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Prentice-Hall.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="93" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="95" w:name="ref-Carretero2017DigComp21" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Carretero, S., Vuorikari, R., &amp; Punie, Y. (2017).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">DigComp 2.1: The digital competence framework for citizens with eight proficiency levels and examples of use</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Joint Research Centre, European Commission.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId94"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://ideas.repec.org/p/ipt/iptwpa/jrc106281.html</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="95" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="97" w:name="ref-Castelfranchi2017RischioFidarsi" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Castelfranchi, C., &amp; Falcone, R. (2017). Il rischio nel fidarsi. La fiducia nel rischiare. Equilibratori cognitivi del comportamento.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Sistemi Intelligenti</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">2</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, 295–312.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId96"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1422/87756</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="97" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="99" w:name="ref-Castelfranchi2002Fondamenti" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Castelfranchi, C., Mancini, F., &amp; Miceli, M. (2002).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Fondamenti di cognitivismo clinico</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Bollati Boringhieri.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId98"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">http://books.google.it/books?id=uXSTAAAACAAJ</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="99" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="101" w:name="ref-Castelfranchi1980Linguaggio" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Castelfranchi, C., &amp; Parisi, D. (1980).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Linguaggio, conoscenze e scopi</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Il Mulino.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId100"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">http://books.google.it/books?id=dhUMAQAAIAAJ</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="101" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="103" w:name="ref-Castelfranchi1998Bugie" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Castelfranchi, C., &amp; Poggi, I. (1998).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Bugie, finzioni, sotterfugi: Per una scienza dell’inganno</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Carocci.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId102"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">http://books.google.it/books?id=srm5AQAACAAJ</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="103" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="105" w:name="ref-Compeau1995ComputerSelfEfficacy" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Compeau, D. R., &amp; Higgins, C. A. (1995). Computer self-efficacy: Development of a measure and initial test.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">MIS Quarterly</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">19</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(2), 189–211.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId104"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.2307/249688</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="105" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="106" w:name="ref-Conte1995CognitiveAction" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Conte, R., &amp; Castelfranchi, C. (1995).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Cognitive and social action</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. UCL Press.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="106" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="108" w:name="ref-Davis1989PerceivedU" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Davis, F. D. (1989). Perceived usefulness, perceived ease of use, and user acceptance of information technology.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">MIS Quarterly</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">13</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(3), 319–340.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId107"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.2307/249008</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="108" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="110" w:name="ref-Davison1983TheThirdP" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Davison, W. P. (1983). The third-person effect in communication.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Public Opinion Quarterly</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">47</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(1), 1–15.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId109"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1086/268763</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="110" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="112" w:name="ref-Unknown2024EUAI" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">EU AI act (regulation (EU) 2024/1689)</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. (2024). European Union.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId111"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/1689/oj</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="112" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="113" w:name="ref-Falcone2008Fiducia" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Falcone, R., &amp; Castelfranchi, C. (2008). Fiducia e sfiducia. In I. Poggi (Ed.),</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">La mente del cuore. Le emozioni nel lavoro, nella scuola, nella vita</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(pp. 89–111). Armando Editore.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="113" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="115" w:name="X5f49c550fdb2ee0960e2866d39df238e0cd68e2" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Frenkenberg, A., &amp; Hochman, G. (2025). It’s scary to use it, it’s scary to refuse it: The psychological dimensions of AI adoption—anxiety, motives, and dependency.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Systems</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">13</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(2), 82.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId114"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.3390/systems13020082</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="115" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="116" w:name="ref-Hall1987CBAM" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Hall, G. E., &amp; Hord, S. M. (1987).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Change in schools: Facilitating the process</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. State University of New York Press.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="116" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="118" w:name="ref-Honicke2016Academicse" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Honicke, T., &amp; Broadbent, J. (2016). Academic self-efficacy: From educational theory to instructional practice.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Educational Research Review</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">17</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, 63–84.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId117"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.edurev.2015.11.002</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="118" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="119" w:name="ref-Jenkins2006Convergence" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Jenkins, H. (2006).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Convergence culture: Where old and new media collide</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. New York University Press.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="119" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="121" w:name="ref-Jenkins2009ParticipatoryBook" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Jenkins, H. (2009).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Confronting the challenges of participatory culture: Media education for the 21st century</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. MIT Press.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId120"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://direct.mit.edu/books/oa-monograph/3204/Confronting-the-Challenges-of-Participatory</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="121" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="122" w:name="ref-Jenkins2015Participat" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Jenkins, H., Ito, M., &amp; boyd, danah. (2015).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Participatory culture in a networked era: A conversation on youth, learning, commerce, and politics</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Polity Press.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="122" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="124" w:name="ref-Jenkins2009ParticipatoryReport" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Jenkins, H., Purushotma, R., Clinton, K., Weigel, M., &amp; Robison, A. (2009).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Confronting the challenges of participatory culture: Media education for the 21st century</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. MacArthur Foundation.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId123"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://www.macfound.org/media/article_pdfs/jenkins_white_paper.pdf</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="124" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="126" w:name="ref-Miceli1989CognitiveValues" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Miceli, M., &amp; Castelfranchi, C. (1989). A cognitive approach to values.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Journal for the Theory of Social Behaviour</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">19</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(2), 169–193.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId125"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-5914.1989.tb00143.x</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="126" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="128" w:name="ref-Miceli1995DifeseMente" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Miceli, M., &amp; Castelfranchi, C. (1995).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Le difese della mente: Profili cognitivi</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Carocci.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId127"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">http://books.google.it/books?id=BazbPAAACAAJ</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="128" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="130" w:name="ref-Miceli2002MindFuture" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Miceli, M., &amp; Castelfranchi, C. (2002). The mind and the future: The (negative) power of expectations.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Theory &amp; Psychology</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">12</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(3), 335–366.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId129"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1177/0959354302012003015</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="130" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="131" w:name="ref-Munari1977Fantasia" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Munari, B. (1977).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Fantasia. Invenzione, creativit</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">à</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">e immaginazione nella comunicazione visiva</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Laterza.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="131" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="133" w:name="ref-Paul2000TheThirdP" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Paul, B., Salwen, M. B., &amp; Dupagne, M. (2000). The third-person effect: A meta-analysis of the perceptual hypothesis.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Mass Communication and Society</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">3</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(1), 57–85.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId132"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1207/s15327825mcs0301_04</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="133" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="135" w:name="ref-Perloff1999TheThirdP" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Perloff, R. M. (1999). The third-person effect: A critical review and synthesis.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Media Psychology</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">1</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(4), 353–378.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId134"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1207/s1532785xmep0104_4</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="135" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="137" w:name="ref-Poggi2006ParoleCorpo" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Poggi, I. (2006).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Le parole del corpo: Introduzione alla comunicazione multimodale</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Carocci.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId136"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">http://books.google.it/books?id=-cmKAAAACAAJ</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="137" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="138" w:name="ref-Poggi2008MenteCuore" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Poggi, I. (Ed.). (2008).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">La mente del cuore: Le emozioni nel lavoro, nella scuola, nella vita</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Armando Editore.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="138" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="139" w:name="ref-Poggi2022PsicologiaComunicazione" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Poggi, I. (2022).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Psicologia della comunicazione: La mente, il corpo, gli altri</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Mondadori.</w:t></w:r></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="139" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="141" w:name="ref-Scherer2019TechnologyAcceptance" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Scherer, R., Siddiq, F., &amp; Tondeur, J. (2019). The technology acceptance model (TAM): A meta-analytic structural equation modeling approach to explaining teachers’ adoption of digital technology in education.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Computers &amp; Education</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">128</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">, 13–35.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId140"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compedu.2018.09.009</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="141" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="143" w:name="ref-Venkatesh2000ATheoretic" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Venkatesh, V., &amp; Davis, F. D. (2000). A theoretical extension of the technology acceptance model: Four longitudinal field studies.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">Management Science</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">46</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(2), 186–204.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId142"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.1287/mnsc.46.2.186.11926</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="143" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="145" w:name="ref-Venkatesh2003UserAccept" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Venkatesh, V., Morris, M. G., Davis, G. B., &amp; Davis, F. D. (2003). User acceptance of information technology: Toward a unified view.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">MIS Quarterly</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">,</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">27</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">(3), 425–478.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId144"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://doi.org/10.2307/30036540</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="145" /><w:bookmarkStart w:id="147" w:name="ref-Vuorikari2016DigComp20" /><w:p><w:pPr><w:pStyle w:val="Bibliography" /></w:pPr><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">Vuorikari, R., Punie, Y., Carretero, S., &amp; Van den Brande, L. (2016).</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:r><w:rPr><w:i /><w:iCs /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">DigComp 2.0: The digital competence framework for citizens. Update phase 1: The conceptual reference model</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve">. Joint Research Centre, European Commission.</w:t></w:r><w:r><w:t xml:space="preserve"> </w:t></w:r><w:hyperlink r:id="rId146"><w:r><w:rPr><w:rStyle w:val="Hyperlink" /></w:rPr><w:t xml:space="preserve">https://ideas.repec.org/p/ipt/iptwpa/jrc101254.html</w:t></w:r></w:hyperlink></w:p><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="147" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="148" /><w:bookmarkEnd w:id="149" /><w:sectPr w:rsidR="00FC693F" w:rsidRPr="0006063C" w:rsidSect="00034616"><w:pgSz w:h="15840" w:w="12240" /><w:pgMar w:bottom="1440" w:footer="720" w:gutter="0" w:header="720" w:left="1800" w:right="1800" w:top="1440" /><w:cols w:space="720" /><w:docGrid w:linePitch="360" /></w:sectPr></w:body></w:document>